Guide to the Betty Grover Eisner Papers SC0924
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Betty Grover Eisner papers
1927-2002
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Eisner, Betty Grover
Eisner, Willard D.
SC0924
10 Linear Feet
Papers documenting Betty Grover Eisner's career in clinical psychology and experimental use of LSD and other drugs. Includes narrative reports and audio recordings of drug therapy sessions, articles and conference papers, book manuscripts, journals, legal documents, journals, personal and professional correspondence, and other materials.
Biography
Betty Grover Eisner (1915-2004), a clinical psychologist best known for her experiments with LSD and other psychoactive drugs, was born Helen Elizabeth Grover in Kansas City, MO. After completing high school in Kansas City, she attended Stanford University and earned a B.A. in political science in 1937. She volunteered with the Red Cross during World War II, then spent a year in the late 1940s traveling Europe, Asia, and Africa with her first husband, fellow Stanford graduate Will Eisner. She documented their trip in a series of columns published in the Los Angeles Times.
Eisner earned a Ph.D. in clinical psychology from the University of California, Los Angeles, in 1956. She completed her dissertation on the psychology of infertile women, but by the time she graduated her primary professional interest had shifted to the use of LSD as an aid to psychotherapy. She conducted LSD experiments with Dr. Sidney Cohen at a Veterans' Administration hospital in Los Angeles, and later established a private psychotherapy practice in Santa Monica. After psychiatric research with LSD was banned in the United States in the late 1960s, Eisner experimented with using other drugs to promote psychological breakthroughs in patients, including ketamine and injectable Ritalin. Other treatments favored by Eisner included the inhalation of carbogen (a mix of 70% oxygen and 30% carbon dioxide), hot mineral baths, massage, and "blasting," a technique in which a patient was encouraged to release hostility by yelling while muffled by a washcloth.
In 1976, one of Eisner's patients died following mineral bath treatment and blasting therapy. A wrongful death investigation ensued, as well an ethics investigation by the American Psychological Association. The Psychology Examining Committee of the California Board of Medical Quality Assurance revoked Eisner's license to practice in 1978. Eisner twice attempted to have her license restored in the early 1980s. Both attempts were unsuccessful.
Eisner was the author of The Unused Potential of Marriage and Sex, published in 1970, as well as an unpublished book based on her group therapy work, I Can't, You Can't, But We Can. During the late 1950s and early 1960s, she authored several journal articles and conference papers on her use of LSD and other drugs in psychotherapy In 2002, she wrote a memoir titled Remembrances of LSD Therapy Past. Although unpublished, this memoir is available on the World Wide Web. Eisner also wrote song lyrics in the 1970s under the pseudonym Rev. B. Later in life, she wrote poetry under the name Abigail Bradbury. She and her second husband, Bill Micks, helped to found the Center for Learning, a school for the teaching of English in Mexico.
Arrangement
The collection consists of six series: Series 1: Personal and Family Papers; Series 2: Writing; Series 3: Correspondence; Series 4: Legal Files; Series 5: Therapy and Research Files; and Series 6: Audio Materials.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Betty Grover Eisner, 2001.
Access
With the exception of Series 2, Series 3 and the world trip materials in Series 1, access to the collection is restricted according to the Department's Access to Health Information of Individuals Policy. Please contact the University Archivist for more information.
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers document Betty Grover Eisner's career in clinical psychology as well as the intersection of her career with her personal life. Included are detailed narrative reports on Eisner's use of LSD and other drugs in conjunction with psychotherapy; audio tapes of drug sessions; numerous articles and conference papers as well as drafts of two books by Eisner; dream journals, free association writing, and other personal writing; legal papers and supporting documents related to an investigation of Eisner for wrongful death and the subsequent revocation of her professional license; and professional and family correspondence. Prominent correspondents include Sidney J. Cohen, Herman Denber, Albert Hoffman, Krishnamurti, Anais Nin, Ron Sandison, and Lewis Terman.
Group psychoanalysis; Group psychotherapy; Psychoanalysis; Correspondence.; sound recordings; Psychotherapy; Psychologists; Articles.; LSD (Drug) -- Therapeutic use; Eisner, Betty Grover; Eisner, Willard D.; Abramson, Harold A. (Harold Alexander), 1899-1980; Cohen, Sidney; Denber, Herman C. B. (Herman Cecil B.); Eisner, Betty Grover; Eisner, Willard D.; Harman, Willis W.; Hofmann, Albert; Jung, C. G. (Carl Gustav); Krishnamurti, J. (Jiddu); Nin, Anaïs; Sandison, Ronald; Terman, Lewis Madison
- Personal and family papers, 1927-1987; Series 1
  Series Description
  This series includes a variety of materials related to Eisner's early education, marriage, and family life. Included are report cards from Kansas City public schools and Stanford University and a scrapbook of Stanford Daily clippings which documents Eisner's involvement in campus life from 1933-1937.
  The correspondence in this series is of a highly personal nature, particularly the correspondence which documents Eisner's relationship with her first husband, Will Eisner, in the years immediately prior to his death from lung cancer in 1965. Betty's correspondence with Will's family is also intensely personal, discussing the couple's marital difficulties in detail.
  Also included is personal writing by Eisner, including a diary of dreams and free association writing, both of which appear to reflect her growing interest in psychology prior to enrolling in UCLA's clinical psychology Ph.D. program.
  There is also a subseries comprised of material created by or about Will Eisner. It includes correspondence, documentation of his employment at the Rand Corporation and SRI, personal writings on his experiences with psychotherapy, and documents related to his estate.
  A second subseries contains materials related to a year-long trip taken by Will and Betty Eisner in 1948 and 1949. Destinations included Europe, India, and Egypt. During this trip, letters that Betty ostensibly wrote to her family were published as a Los Angeles Times column titled "Travel Letter from Betty." Included in this series are complete manuscripts for these columns and a scrapbook with newspaper clippings of the published column. There are also letters from Will Eisner to his family while abroad, correspondence documenting a dispute over money that was seized from the Eisners at the Indian border, and Betty's correspondence with met while traveling.
  Arrangement
  Files are arranged alphabetically within each subseries.
  - Advertisement for illuminated darning egg invented and sold by Betty and Will Eisner, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence re: attempt to purchase a Studebaker, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence with Eisner family [1 of 3], 1957-1973 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence with Eisner family [2 of 3], 1957-1973 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence with Eisner family [3 of 3], 1957-1973 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence re: separation and Will's illness [1 of 2], 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence re: separation and Will's illness [2 of 2], 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence re: Will's illness, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, condolence letters re: Will's death [1 of 2], 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, condolence letters re: Will's death [2 of 2], 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Mexico investments, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Personal writing, diary re: relationship with Will, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Personal writing, dreams [1 of 2], 1947-1952 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Personal writing, dreams [2 of 2], 1947-1952 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Personal writing, free association, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Personal writing, free associaion (24 hour association), 1947 August 9 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Personal writing, free associaion, 1951-1955 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Personal writing, UCLA workshop, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Promotional material for "song poetry" performance by Eisner (as Abigail Bradbury) and Charlotte Lancaster, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Psychological tests, Will and Betty, 1947-1951, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Report cards, 1925-1936 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Rorschach test, Helen W. Grover (mother of Betty), 1950 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Scrapbook of Stanford Daily clippings, circa 1933-1937 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Songwriting, copyright registration forms plus index cards with song titles, 1971-1979 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Will Eisner, 1927-1967
    - Correspondence, incoming, 1947-1963 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Eisner, Milton (Will's father), death, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Employment at Rand and SRI, 1959-1963, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Estate (1 of 2), 1959-1967 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Estate (2 of 2), 1959-1967 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Personal documents, 1927-1965 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Writings on therapy, 1949-1950, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - World Trip, 1948-1967
    - Correspondence from Will to family during trip [1 of 3], 1948-1949 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence from Will to family during trip [2 of 3], 1948-1949 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence from Will to family during trip [3 of 3], 1948-1949 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence re: money confiscated in India, 1949-1951 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence with people met on world trip, 1949-1967 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, writing, and miscellaneous materials, 1948-1949 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Newspaper column, correspondence about, 1948-1949 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Newspaper column, manuscripts [1 of 2], 1948-1949 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Newspaper column, manuscripts [2 of 2], 1948-1949 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Newspaper column, scrapbook of Los Angeles Times clippings, 1948-1949 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Writing, 1957-2002, undated; Series 2
  The bulk of this series consists of journal articles, conference papers, and other professional writing by Eisner. Most of these works have been published, although some are unpublished manuscripts. There is also a copy of a manuscript for Eisner's book The Unused Potential of Marriage and Sex (published 1970) and an unpublished manuscript based on Eisner's experiences with group therapy titled I Can't, You Can't, But We Can.
  Later in life Eisner pursued creative writing and composed poetry under the name Abigail Bradbury. Although there are no examples of her poetry in this series, there are manuscripts of a series of fables, titled "New Fables for New Times," written by Eisner in the early 1990s.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - "Current Thinking on LSD Therapy" (with Sidney Cohen), 1957 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - "Psychotherapy with Lysergic Acid Diethylamide" (written with Sidney Cohen), 1958 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - "Subjective Reports on Lysergic Acid Experiences... " (with Sidney Cohen and Lionel Fischman), 1958 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - "The Influence of LSD on Unconscious Activity", 1961 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - "Some Psychological Differences Between Fertile and Infertile Women", 1963 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - "Notes on the Use of Drugs to Facilitate Group Psychotherapy", 1964 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - "Psychedelics and People as Adjuncts to Psychotherapy", 1964 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - "The Importance of the Non-Verbal", 1965 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - The Unused Potential of Marriage and Sex, original manuscript [1 of 3], 1970 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - The Unused Potential of Marriage and Sex, original manuscript [2 of 3], 1970 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - The Unused Potential of Marriage and Sex, original manuscript [3 of 3], 1970 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - The Unused Potential of Marriage and Sex, 1970 (Box 5, Folder no folder)
  - "The Group as a Means and Matrix for Change", 1971 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - See You To-Morrow, by the Children of Mexcales (words by Betty Eisner, pictures by Les McCann), 1972 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - "The Use of an Alpha Feedback Machine in a Therapeutic Problem Solving Setting" (with Jonathan D. Melvin), 1972 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - "The Two Faces of Man's Problem Today", 1974 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - "Networking Provides Realtime Application Upgrade from TRT-11 to VMS" (with Jonathan D. Melvin), 1987 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - "New Fables for New Times," manuscripts and drafts [1 of 2], circa 1987 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - "New Fables for New Times," manuscripts and drafts [2 of 2], circa 1987 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - "New Fables for New Times," manuscripts and drafts [3 of 3], circa 1987 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - "Huaulta -- Place Where Eagles Are Born," manuscript and drafts, circa 1994 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - "Physical and Psychical Loading," paper read at Society for Scientific Exploration meeting, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Response to Daniel J. Benor's comments on "loading" and "telesomatic reactions", 1996 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - "The Sick Role Versus the Dying Role," (written with Humphrey Osmond), 1996 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - "Body Work and Psychological Healing", 1997 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - "Set, Setting, and Matrix", 1997 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Excerpt from Remembrance of LSD Therapy Past, 2002 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - I Can't, You Can't, But We Can, third draft (final?) [1 of 3], undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - I Can't, You Can't, But We Can, third draft (final?) [2 of 3], undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - I Can't, You Can't, But We Can, third draft (final?) [3 of 3], undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Living in the Now, foreword, chapter 1, and appendix D, undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - "Observations on Possible Order Within the Unconscious", undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - "Observations on the Psychotherapeutic Use of Ritalin", undated (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - "The Paradox of Carroll John Daly," manuscript and research material (includes manuscript of a Daly short story), undated (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - "Parallel Experiences", undated (Box 6, Folder 17)
- Correspondence, 1946-1998; Series 3
  This series consists primarily of Eisner's professional correspondence. However, since Eisner developed close friendships with many colleagues who shared her interest in LSD and other drug research, much of the content is of a personal nature. Some files also include clippings and other materials. Researchers should note the presence of additional correspondence in other series, particularly in Series 1: Family Papers.
  Arranged alphabetically by last name of correspondent.
  - Abramson, Harold, 1957-1968, 1994 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Cohen, Sidney J. [1 of 2], 1967-1997, undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Cohen, Sidney J. [2 of 2], 1967-1997, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Denber, Herman [1 of 3], 1957-1998 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Denber, Herman [2 of 3], 1957-1998 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Denber, Herman [3 of 3], 1957-1998 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Graf, Stanya, 1965-1993 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Harman, Willis, 1957-1997 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Hoffman, Albert [1 of 2], 1976-1997 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Hoffman, Albert [2 of 2], 1976-1997 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Hubbard, Al, 1957-1965, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Jung, Carl, 1952-1972 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Krishnamurti, J. [1 of 3], 1946-1986 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Krishnamurti, J. [2 of 3], 1946-1986 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Krishnamurti, J. [3 of 3], 1946-1996 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Martin, Joyce, 1957, 1963-1970 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Naranjo, Caludio, 1965, 1981 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Nin, Anais, correspondence and clippings, 1958-1992 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Osment, Humphrey, 1961-1970 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Powers, Tom and Zip Riley, 1957-1995 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Sandison, Ron and Margaret [1 of 3], 1958-1997 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Sandison, Ron and Margaret [2 of 3], 1958-1997 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Sandison, Ron and Margaret [3 of 3], 1958-1997 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Terman, Lewis, 1946-1956 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence (Box 8, Folder 15)
- Legal files, 1975-1994; Series 4
  Files in this series relate to legal action against Eisner following a patient's death in 1976. In addition to the wrongful death investigation that followed, Eisner faced an ethics investigation by the California State Psychological Association and the American Psychological Association, as well as an investigation and hearing before the Psychology Examining Committee of the California Board of Medical Quality Assurance. As a result of this investigation, her professional license was revoked in 1978. At Eisner's request, relicensing hearings were held in 1980 and 1983. In both cases the Psychology Examining Committee refused to restore her license. This series includes copies of legal documents, correspondence, and other supporting material collected by Eisner.
  Also included is one file on a small claims court case filed against a patient in 1973.
  Files are arranged chronologically within each subseries.
  - Small claims court case, 1973-1974
    - Small claims court case against Karen Otte, 1973-1974 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Wrongful death investigation and lawsuits, 1976-1984
    - Inquest and wrongful death lawsuit [1 of 3], 1976-1984 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Inquest and wrongful death lawsuit [2 of 3], 1976-1984 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Inquest and wrongful death lawsuit [3 of 3], 1976-1984 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - State of California et. al. v. Eisner, Declarations in Opposition to Motion for Preliminary Injunction, 1977 [1 of 2] (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - State of California et. al. v. Eisner, Declarations in Opposition to Motion for Preliminary Injunction, 1977 [2 of 2] (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - State of California et. al. v. Eisner, declarations of witnesses, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - State of California et. al. v. Eisner, Objections and Motion to Strike Proffered Evidence, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - State of California et. al. v. Eisner, other legal filings, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Unsworn statement of Betty Eisner, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Insurance company lawsuit [1 of 3], 1981-1984 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Insurance company lawsuit [2 of 3], 1981-1984 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Insurance company lawsuit [3 of 3], 1981-1984 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Insurance company lawsuit, Betty Eisner deposition, 1982 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Insurance company lawsuit, William Raymond Micks deposition, 1982 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Board of Medical Quality Assurance hearings and license revocation, 1975-1994
    - Accusation against Eisner, 1977 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Board of Medical Quality Assurance hearing, background materials [1 of 2], 1975-1978, undated (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Board of Medical Quality Assurance hearing, background materials [2 of 2], 1975-1978, undated (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Affidavits given by Eisner patients to Board of Medical Quality Assurance, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Board of Medical Quality Assurance hearing, statements by Eisner and patients [1 of 2], 1977 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Board of Medical Quality Assurance hearing, statements by Eisner and patients [2 of 2], 1977 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Board of Medical Quality Assurance hearing, legal filings, 1977-1978 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Board of Medical Quality Assurance decision against Eisner, 1978 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Eisner v. Psychology Examining Committee, legal filings, 1979 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Relicensing hearing, 1980 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Relicensing hearing, exhibits, 1980 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Relicensing hearing, transcripts and decision, 1980 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Relicensing attempt, affidavits and letters of support, 1983 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Relicensing attempt, statements on behalf of Eisner, 1983 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Petition for license restoration and correspondence re: hearing, 1983-1984 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Relicensing hearing, transcript, 1984 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Relicensing hearing, decision and follow-up, 1984-1985 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Relicensing attempts, miscellaneous materials [1 of 2], 1979-1994 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Relicensing attempts, miscellaneous materials [2 of 2], 1979-1994 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - American Psychological Association and California State Psychological Associtation ethics investigations, 1976-1980
    - American Psychological Association Committee Hearing [1 of 4], 1976-1979 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - American Psychological Association Committee Hearing [2 of 4], 1976-1979 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - American Psychological Association Committee Hearing [3 of 4], 1976-1979 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - American Psychological Association Committee Hearing [4 of 4], 1976-1979 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - American Psychological Association and California State Psychological Association Ethics Investigations [1 of 4], 1977-1980 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - American Psychological Association and California State Psychological Association Ethics Investigations [2 of 4], 1977-1980 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - American Psychological Association and California State Psychological Association Ethics Investigations [3 of 4], 1977-1980 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - American Psychological Association and California State Psychological Association Ethics Investigations [4 of 4], 1977-1980 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence re: legal cases, 1977-1979 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous papers re: legal cases (Box 12, Folder 8)
- Therapy and research files, 1946-1995, undated; Series 5
  The bulk of this series consists of Eisner's detailed narrative accounts of therapy sessions, the majority of which involved the use of LSD, ritalin, ketamine, and other psychoactive drugs. Early session reports include descriptions of Eisner's own use of these drugs; later, she focused on her experiences facilitating group therapy sessions in which participants were given drugs in an attempt to break through psychological barriers. In the late 1960s and early 1970s, these sessions increasingly incorporated other non-mainstream therapies, including mineral baths, "blasting" (a technique in which patients immersed in a mineral bath were encouraged to yell and scream while muffled by a washcloth), and massage.
  There is also a subseries related to Eisner's involvement with the Sequoia Seminar. The Sequoia Seminar was established by Stanford University Law professor Harry Rathbun and his wife, Emalia, in the 1930s. Its original goal was the study of historical records of the life of Jesus in a non-religious context. Many of Betty Eisner's early LSD subjects were Sequoia Seminar participants.
  Arrangement varies by subseries.
- Audio materials, 1957-1972, undated; Series 6
  Audio recordings, primarily of drug sessions conducted by Eisner in the late 1950s and early 1960s. The recordings were not played back during processing.
  - Therapy sessions
    Conditions Governing Access
    access to the collection is restricted according to the Department's Access to Health Information of Individuals Policy. Please contact the University Archives for more information.
  - Events and Talks
    - Eisner, Betty, reading The Prophet, undated; 18.43; 1 audiotape reel(s) (Box 18)
    - Eisner, Betty, seminar, 1972-05-14; 18.44; 1 audiotape reel(s) (Box 18)
    - Eisner, Betty, talk at UCLA psychology seminar, 1971-04-25; 18.42; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 18)
    - The Sacred Mushroom Chant, Ch. 11, 1965-06-15; 18.25; 1 audiotape reel(s) (Box 18)
    - Arrowhead session (snow), undated; 18.26; 1 audiotape reel(s) (Box 18)